Oliver Otis Howard Papers M091 M091
George J. Mitchell Department of Special Collections & Archives, Bowdoin College Library, Brunswick, Maine 04011
- M91.13: Personal records, 1866-1900, undated, M91.13; 0.5 linear feet
  - Ephemera. re the S.S. Spree (Box 43, Folder 102)
  - Funerary notices (in memoria). Manuscript - Grey, Bessie (Box 43, Folder 103)
  - Funerary notices (in memoria). Printed: Ackerson, John Walter; Andrus, Maude Griffith; Cannon, M.M.; Collins, George J.; Dayton, George M.; Drury, Thomas; Freis, Andre; Gould, Chessman; Hancock, Winfield Scott; Kerr, William H.; Landers, John; Livingston, Mortimer; Mower, Joseph A.; Newlands, Francis; Norton, William; Pratt, Sophia M.; Slocum, Henry W.; Stirling, Fannie Marcum; Sumner, Hannah W. Forster; Taylor, William Norton; Topping, M. Howell (Box 43, Folder 104)
  - Literary material. Essays written at Bowdoin (Box 43, Folder 105)
  - Literary material. Fragments, autobiographical and re Virgil (Box 43, Folder 106)
  - Literary material. Lectures by Howard, Contracts for (Box 43, Folder 107)
  - Literary material. Lectures by Howard. Prospectuses, etc. (Box 43, Folder 108)
  - Literary material. Lectures by Howard. Receipts for payment (Box 43, Folder 109)
  - Literary material. Lectures by Howard. Lectures by other speakers (Box 43, Folder 110)
  - Literary material. Lectures by Howard. Poems, by other authors (Box 43, Folder 111)
  - Literary material. Lectures by Howard. Poems, "Written on the death of a Father - By a son" O.O. Howard (Box 43, Folder 112)
  - Literary material. Lectures by Howard. Re Zachary Taylor by Howard - Account of the marriage of Jefferson Davis to Knox Taylor (daughter of Zachary Taylor) as told by Mary D. Hancock (Box 43, Folder 113)
  - Literary material. Lectures by Howard. Re Zachary Taylor by Howard - general (Box 43, Folder 114)
  - Literary material. Lectures by Howard. Works by Howard, prospectuses, etc. (Box 43, Folder 115)
  - Literary material. Lectures by Howard. Works by other authors, prospectuses, etc. (Box 43, Folder 116)
  - Political material. Congress - bills and resolutions re Absalom Baird, Josephine P. Kelton (Box 43, Folder 117)
  - Political material. Congress - copies of memoranda re Gen. Wm. Thos. Sweeney - sent to David B. Hill in connections with legislation to get a pension for his widow Eugenia Sweeney (Box 43, Folder 118)
  - Political material. General's tour for presidential elections of 1896 in support of Republican Party (Box 43, Folder 119)
  - Political material. Miscellaneous (Box 43, Folder 120)
  - Political material. Union League Club (Box 43, Folder 121)
  - Programs, etc. Banquet for Howard on his 70th birthday (1900 Nov 8) (Box 43, Folder 122)
  - Programs, etc. Centennial celebration of the establishment of the capitol in the District of Columbia (1900) (Box 43, Folder 123)
  - Programs, etc. Commemorative dinners and meetings - miscellaneous (Box 43, Folder 124)
  - Programs, etc. International exhibition (U.S. Centennial Commission, 1876) (Box 43, Folder 125)
  - Programs, etc. Religious services (Box 43, Folder 126)
  - Temperance. Abstinence pledges (Box 43, Folder 127)
  - Temperance. General (Box 43, Folder 128)
  - Temperance. Sons of Temperance (Box 43, Folder 129)
- M91.14: Diaries, 1847-1893, M91.14; 0.5 linear feet
  Engagement book (through 1893) and diaries (1847-1861) kept by Howard, together with the diary of Major Thomas Ward Osborn. Maj. Osborn's diary has been published as The Fiery Trail: a Union Officer's Account of Sherman's Last Campaigns.
  - Diary-Part 1-1847-1855; from Feb. also 20, '47 to Sept. 24, '47 (in full), also from Feb. 17, '50 to Dec. 16, '55 (incomplete) (Volume-folio 1)
  - Diary-Part 2-1847-1861; from Feb. 20, '47 to Sept. 20, '48 (in full), also from Jan. 9, '60 to March 16, '61 (incomplete) (Volume-folio 2)
  - Diary of Maj. T.W. Osborn, U.S.V. Operations of the Army of the Tennessee, in the Carolina Campaign, 1865 (Volume-folio 3)
  - Engagement book, 1886-1893 (Volume-folio 4)
- M91.15: Images, 1900, 1904, undated, M91.15; 0.5 linear feet
  This series is separated into material type, including block print, engravings, heliotype, photographs and published photographs of Howard. Most of the images are undated portrait views of Howard in uniform, though photographs of Howard with family members are also included. Of note is a photograph of Howard with Chief Joseph taken in 1904. The images are from a variety of sources.
  Arranged alphabetically by image type.
  - Block print: Portrait view of Howard signed by Hawthorne Smyth (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Engravings (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Heliotype: portrait view of Howard from plate removed from History of Bowdoin College (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Photographs: Howard in uniform (1 of 2) (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Photographs: Howard in uniform (2 of 2) (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Photograph: Howard - miscellaneous (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Photograph: Howard with Chief Joseph at the Carlisle Indian School, 1904 (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - Photograph: Howard with family members (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Published photographs (Box 44, Folder 9)